Guide to the Leonard Sloan Torgoff Papers ALBA.109
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Leonard Sloan Torgoff Papers
1928-1936
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Torgoff, Leonard Sloan, 1916-1937
ALBA.109
0.25 Linear Feet (1 box)
Leonard Sloan Torgoff (1916-1937) went to Spain in January 1937 to join the International Brigades in the Spanish Civil War. The following month he was killed when his truck was ambushed during the Battle of Jarama. This collection contains correspondence and other materials dating from Torgoff's high school and college years, including examples of Torgoff's published and unpublished writings.
Provenance
The Leonard Sloan Torgoff Papers were donated to the Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives in 1985 by Carl Torgoff, Leonard Torgoff's brother. This collection came to New York University in January 2001 as part of the original acquisition of ALBA collections, formerly housed at Brandeis University.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Tamiment Library & Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives for more information and to schedule an appointment, tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu or 212-998-2630.
Historical/Biographical Note
Leonard Sloan Torgoff was born in 1916. While attending Brooklyn College as an English major, Torgoff organized workers and led a successful strike against Feltman's Restaurant and hotdog stands in Coney Island, for whom he worked. When his mother died in January 1934, Torgoff took a leave of absence from school. Making his living as a plumber, he committed himself to becoming a writer and began to practice his craft. After a hitchhiking trip in Canada, Torgoff enrolled in night school at City College back in New York. In the summer of 1934 he left home again, this time traveling cross-country to Arizona, ending up enrolled in college at University of Denver in Colorado for the school year 1934-1935. There he wrote "Moods and Muses," subtitled "a literary column," for the college newspaper, The Clarion, in which he reviewed art, plays, jazz, food, poetry and books, and offered observations on beauty, love and war, among other topics. During this time Torgoff also continued writing poems, essays and short stories. Torgoff grew homesick for New York, however, and returned home after a year in Colorado.
In January 1937, Torgoff sailed to Spain on the S.S. Champlain to join the International Brigades in the Spanish Civil War. He was assigned to the Abraham Lincoln Brigade, and in February 1937 was in one of two trucks that were attacked as they drove into the fascist lines during the Battle of Jarama. Reports initially listed Torgoff as having been taken prisoner and executed, but subsequently it was established that he was killed in the course of the ambush.
Torgoff went by the nickname Leo or Leon; Sloan was his mother's maiden name.
Scope and Content Note
Series I: Subject Files, 1928-1936. This series contains correspondence and other materials dating from Torgoff's high school and college years. Letters from Torgoff are mainly to women friends, including one to "Miss Stack," in which he describes his aspirations as a writer. General correspondence consists almost entirely of letters addressed to Torgoff, principally from women with whom he attended school in Colorado. Memorabilia includes a postcard picturing Feltman's Restaurant of Coney Island (where Torgoff worked and against which he led a successful strike) and a program for the American premiere of the film, Carnival in Flanders. Also included are Torgoff's high school yearbook and diploma.
S eries II: Writings, 1932-1936. This series contains examples of Torgoff's published and unpublished writings, and includes essays, poetry, short stories, and notes. Also included are Torgoff's "Moods and Muses" columns, written while attending the University of Denver; and a number of papers written for school.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically within each series; correspondence arranged chronologically.
The files are grouped into two series:
Missing Title
I, Subject Files, 1928-1936
II, Writings, 1932-1936.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
ALBA collections at the Tamiment Library.
Two files of materials by and relating to Leonard Sloan Torgoff, including articles and research material about his death in Spain, can be found in the Robert Steck Papers.
Separated Material
Photographs from the Leonard Sloan Torgoff Papers have been transferred to the non-print section of the ALBA collection in the Tamiment Library.
Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939.; Correspondence.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Participation, American.; Articles.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Personal narratives.; Printed ephemera.; Spain. Ejército Popular de la República. Brigada Internacional, XV--Biography; Spain. Ejercito Popular de la Republica. Brigada Internacional, XV; Spain. Ejercito Popular de la Republica. Abraham Lincoln Battalion; Torgoff, Leonard Sloan, 1916-1937
- Series I: Subject Files, 1928-1936
  - Clippings, undated, 1932-1935 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: General, undated, Aug 1928-Sep 1936 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence: Torgoff, Leonard (outgoing), undated, May 1933-Sep 1936 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - High school certificate and diploma, Apr 1932-Jun 1932 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - High school yearbook, Jun 1932 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Memorabilia and membership card, undated, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Series II: Writings, 1932-1936
  - Article (published), May 1935 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Fiction and other prose (typescripts), undated, Dec 1932-Oct 1936 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Moods and Muses: Notes and drafts, 1934-1935 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Moods and Muses: Published articles, Dec 1934-May 1935 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Notes and fragments (handwritten); and sketches, undated, Jan 1934-Feb 1936 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Poetry (handwritten), May 1934 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Poetry (typescripts), undated, Nov 1933-Jun 1935 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - School papers, undated, Jun 1934 (Box 1, Folder 14)